A Finding Aid to the Jaime Davidovich Papers, 1949-2014, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Jaime Davidovich papers
1949-2014
Archives of American Art
Davidovich, Jaime, 1936-2016
AAA.davijaim
Archival Resource Key
2.3 Linear feet
The papers of New York-based, Argentinian born conceptual and performance artist Jaime Davidovich, measure 2.3 linear feet and date from 1949 to 2014. The collection document's Davidovich's transition from Argentina to the United States, his early artistic career in both countries, specific projects and exhibitions, and the way in which Davidovich's work intersected with audiovisual media and the New York avant-garde in the 1960s and 1970s. Papers include biographical materials, correspondence, writings including memoirs, exhibition and project files, scrapbooks, and printed materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated by Jaime Davidovich in 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Biographical / Historical
Jaime Davidovich (1936-2016) was a conceptual and performance artist in New York, N.Y.
Davidovich was born in Buenos Aires, Argentina. As a child, he became ill with rheumatic fever and his parents gave him art materials with which to entertain himself during his months of illness. Davidovich studied at National College in Buenos Aires and graduated from the University of Uruguay in 1961. After graduation, he began teaching in Bahía Blanca, Argentina, and subsequently became the art superintendent at the visual arts school. In 1963 he was given the opportunity to travel to New York by the DiTella Foundation in Buenos Aires, after a grant to study in France fell through at the last minute. In New York he attended the School of Visual Arts and eventually began working as a graphic designer for Random House publishers.
In 1965, Davidovich and his wife, artist Judith Henry, moved to Cleveland, Ohio, where he worked as a graphic designer and began working with video. His first video installation was exhibited at the Akron Art Institute in 1972. Davidovich's fascination with video and television continued when he moved back to New York City and created the nonprofit organization, Artists Television Network (ATN). The network produced television shows for Manhattan's public access channel using the name SoHo Television. Davidovich's avant-garde variety show, The Live! Show, was the organization's most well-known production. Davidovich hosted the show as the character Dr. Videovich, and invited guests including Laurie Anderson, Eric Bogosian, and other creatives.
In 1976, Davidovich and Henry established Wooster Enterprises, a design studio and retail outlet that created conceptual stationary in affiliation with the Fluxus movement. The company closed in 1979, but it's most popular stationary continued to be produced and sold at the Museum of Modern Art.
Scope and Contents
The papers of New York-based, Argentinian born conceptual and performance artist Jaime Davidovich, measure 2.3 linear feet and date from 1949 to 2014. The collection document's Davidovich's transition from Argentina to the United States, his early artistic career in both countries, specific projects and exhibitions, and the way in which Davidovich's work intersected with audiovisual media and the New York avant-garde in the 1960s and 1970s. Papers include biographical materials, correspondence, writings including memoirs, exhibition and project files, scrapbooks, and printed materials.
Biographical materials include Davidovich's contacts in address books, a certificate, curriculum vitae, a membership card, and a report card. A photograph album documents his New York apartment and studio after first coming to New York in the 1960s. Also found are records of the Wooster Street Corporation where Davidovich later lived and had his studio. A small amount of correspondence is with museums, galleries, artists, and curators, notably Julieta Hanono, Ilene Segalove, and Julia Herzberg, and includes early correspondence from Argentina during Davidovich's time as a student and a teacher in Buenos Aires.
Writings include artist statements, lecture note cards, a letter of recommendation, memoir drafts, and a manuscript about Davidovich by Carolyn Kinder Carr. Memoirs provide detailed information about Davidovich's childhood, education, and early career. Files for exhibitions consist of correspondence, notes, gallery floor plans, photographic material, lists of artwork, and exhibition announcements. Project files contain bound project books, proposals, correspondence, notes, sketches, photographic and source material for the Artists' Television Network, Wooster Enterprises, and other projects.
Three scrapbooks record Davidovich's career in fine arts and design. Printed material includes art reproductions, books, brochures and booklets, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, flyers, periodicals, posters, and press releases.
Much of the later correspondence found in the collection is in the form of printed email; later photographic material is in the form of digitially printed photograhs.
The bulk of material related to Davidovich's artworks, especially later ones, and the artworks themselves are located at NYU Fales Library.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as seven series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1949-2007 (Box 1, OVs 3, 5; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1958-2012 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1973, 2001-2009 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 2003-2011 (Box 1, OV 3; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Project Files, circa 1960-2014 (Box 1-2, OVs 4-5; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1960s-circa 1971 (Box 2, OVs 3-4; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 7: Printed Materials, circa 1950s-2009 (Box 2, OVs 3, 5; 0.5 linear feet)
Related Materials
The bulk of the records related to Davidovich's artworks, especially later ones, and artworks themselves, are located in the Jaime Davidovich Collection, 1952-2000, at New York University's Fales Library.
Existence and Location of Copies
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2020 and is available on the Archives of American Art website. Items not digitized include blank pages, blank versos of photographs, address books, some publications for which only the covers and relevant pages may have been digitized, and some of the routine records relating to the 152 Wooster Street Corporation management and sale.
Conceptual artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Sketchbooks; Drawings; Interviews; Performance artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Latino and Latin American artists; Henry, Judith (Henry Davidovich); Artists' Television Network; Wooster Enterprises; Segalove, Ilene, 1950-; Herzberg, Julia P.
- Biographical Material, 1949-2007; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1, OVs 3, 5
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials consist of four address books, a certificate recognizing Davidovich's contributions to Artworks 84 at the Louisiana World's Fair, a curriculum vitae with photos of artwork, a membership card, and a school report card. Also found is a photograph album with images of Davidovich's New York apartment and studio, friends and family, and colleagues from a job at a bookstore. Receipts are for art supplies and artwork purchased by Davidovich with accompanying certificates of antiquity. Records relating to the 152 Wooster Street Corporation, which provided living quarters and studio space for artists including Davidovich, include bylaws, meeting minutes, records of renovations, and other financial and legal records documenting the ownership and management of the building, and the sale of Davidovich's apartment.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  The bulk of this series has been digitized. Material not digitized includes address book, and some receipts, legal documentation, sale records, and other routine repair and management records related to the 152 Wooster Street Corporation.
  - Address Books, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Address Books, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Address Books, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Certificate, 1984 Louisiana World's Fair, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 3, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Membership Card, National Committee of Plastic Arts, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photograph Album, 1963-1964; 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Real Estate, 152 Wooster Street Corporation, 1974-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Real Estate, 152 Wooster Street Corporation, 1997-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Real Estate, 152 Wooster Street Corporation, Cooperative Legal Documents, 1974-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Real Estate, 152 Wooster Street Corporation, Loft Improvement Receipts, 1974-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Real Estate, 152 Wooster Street Corporation, Renovation, 1998-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Real Estate, 152 Wooster Street Corporation, Renovation, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5, Folder 1)
  - Real Estate, 152 Wooster Street Corporation, Sale, 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Receipts, Purchases of Artwork and Art Supplies, 1969-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Report Card, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1958-2012; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is with museums, galleries, and artists, including a several items each from artist Julieta Hanono and curator Julia Herzberg. Correspondence with Ilene Segalove is more extensive with twelve pieces of correspondence discussing Segalove's "TV is OK" Productions among other things. Early correspondence includes letters from Davidovich's tenure as a teacher and superintendent of visual art in Bahía Blanca, Argentina. Also found is the transcript of an interview with Davidovich by Pedro Cuperman during the Latin American Forum at the 2005 Syracuse University Film and Video Festival.
  This series has been digitized in entirety.
  - Argentina, Bahía Blanca (1961), 1958-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Argentina, General, 1958-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Art Spaces Archives Project, 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bronx Museum of the Arts, 2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Getty Research Institute, 2005-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Guggenheim, The Take Blog, 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Hanono, Julieta, 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Herzberg, Julia, 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Segalove, Ilene, circa 1980-circa 1981; 2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Street, Mark, 2009-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Syracuse University/Point of Contact Gallery, 2005-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Teaching Correspondence and Resumes, circa 1962-circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Writings, circa 1973; 2001-2009; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings are generally by Davidovich and include artist statements, note cards and related material for a lecture he delivered at the School of Visual Arts, and a letter of recommendation for Carla Stellweg, curator and consultant for The Latin American Spirit: Art and Artists in the US, 1920-1970 among other exhibitions. Also found are outlines, drafts, and edited manuscripts with questions, of Davidovich's memoirs. The memoirs record events dating from childhood, and document Davidovich's education, his transition to the United States, and the subsequent development of his career. Memoir material includes a photograph of Davidovich with Jorge Luis Borges, and layouts for photographs.
  An untitled manuscript about Davidovich written by Carolyn Kinder Carr is housed at the end of the series.
  - Artist Statements, circa 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Lecture, School of Visual Arts, 2003; 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Letter of Recommendation for Carla Stellweg, 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Memoirs, circa 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Memoirs, 2002-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - About Davidovich by Carolyn Kinder Carr, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Exhibition Files, 2003-2011; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1, OV 3
  Exhibition files include correspondence, gallery floor plans, lists of artwork, exhibition announcements, publicity material, photographs of artwork and a few scattered photos of Davidovich, and other documents related to exhibitions of Davidovich's paintings and video installations. Included are files for Size Matters, a traveling exhibition featuring former World Trade Center Residency participants; and the retrospective Biting the Hand That Feeds You at the Artium Museum in Spain, which includes correspondence with the exhibition curator, Arturo "Fito" Rodriguez.
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged chronologically by exhibition year.
  - Site Matters (2004-2006), Lower Manhattan Cultural Council, 2003-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Ultravideoform (2004)/Jaime Davidovich Television and Video Works: 1970-2007 (2007), Mitchell Algus Gallery, circa 2003-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Odd Lots: Revisiting Gordon Matta-Clark's Fake Estates (2005), Cabinet Magazine, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Odd Lots: Revisiting Gordon Matta-Clark's Fake Estates (2005), Cabinet Magazine, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5, Folder 2)
  - Jaime Davidovich: The Live! Show (2009), Seventeen Gallery, 2008-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Biting the Hand That Feeds You (2010-2011), Artium Museum, circa 2005-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Biting the Hand That Feeds You (2010-2011), Artium Museum, circa 2005-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Biting the Hand That Feeds You (2010-2011), Artium Museum, 2006-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 3, Folder 2)
  - Jaime Davidovich: "The Live! Show" (2010), Cabinet Magazine, 2009-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - The Museum Show (2011), Arnolfini, 2010-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Project and Source Files, circa 1960-2014; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OVs 4-5
  Davidovich's project files contain bound project books consisting primarily of photocopied documents compiled to document specific projects, proposals, correspondence, notes and sketches, source material, and photographic material. The series documents some of Davidovich's most well-known projects including some for the Artists' Television Network which produced The Live! Show, and Wooster Enterprises, the design studio and retail outlet established by Davidovich and Judith Henry in 1976. Also found are portfolios and original artwork Davidovich produced as a designer for various companies, including National Potteries where he served as Design Director.
  Wooster Enterprises records include bound books published by the company, stationary sets, photocopies of a "Sound and Unbound" catalog, a bound set of photocopied invoices, and a publication produced in conjunction with the Wooster Enterprises exhibition at Churner and Churner in 2012.
  Also found are a video notebook with notes and sketches for an unidentified project; a book of sketches and notes labeled "paintings, "backdrops," and "Cleveland 1984," which contains lists, sketches, and notes for a Dr. Videovich art lesson; and proposals for a workshop and a Guggenheim Fellowship. One book produced by the American Museum of the Moving Image includes hand-colored sketches and is housed with three additional loose sketches.
  Source material consists primarily of postcards and photographs of televisions. Many of these have alphanumeric codes attached to, or written on them, which have been retained with the items, although their significance is not known.
  - Artists Talk, Media Noche, 2010-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Artists' Television Network, The Artist and Television Conference, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Artists' Television Network, Evita, A Video Scrapbook, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Artists' Television Network, The Live! Show, circa 1982-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Artists' Television Network, "SoHo, Home of the Avant Garde," Grant Proposal, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Artists' Television Network, "SoHo Project," Press Kit, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Artists' Television Network, "SoHo Television Presents," Press Kit, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Artists' Television Network, TV Magazine, Pilot Issue, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Back Drops," "Paintings 85" Sketchbook, 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Design, National Potteries Portfolio, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Design, National Potteries, Original Artwork, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Design, National Potteries, Original Artwork, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 3, Folder 3)
  - "God", 2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes photos and floor plans of religious buildings, images of logos, and notes.
  - Guggenheim Fellowship Proposal, 2005-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Mamba", 2011-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes drawings, notes, and photographic material.
  - "Mamba", 2012; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5, Folder 3)
  - Source Material, Television Images, circa 1960-circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Source Material, Television Images, circa 1960-circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Source Material, Television Images, circa 1960-circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Source Material, Television Images, circa 1960-circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Source Material, Television Images, circa 1960-circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Source Material, Photographs of Artwork, circa 1960-circa 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Video Notebook for Unidentified Project, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Video Tape" Explaining Davidovich's Work, 1972-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Includes notes on "The Road," an application and contract with Manhattan Cable TV, and news articles on video art.
  - Visual Studies Workshop Proposal, circa 1983-circa 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Includes slides of artwork for a The Live! Show installation.
  - Wooster Enterprises, 1989; circa 2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Wooster Enterprises, Bound Invoices, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Wooster Enterprises Publication, "Jaime Davidovich From Cover to Cover", 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Wooster Enterprises, Stationary, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Scrapbooks, 1960s-circa 1971; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 2, OVs 3-4
  Three scrapbooks, containing mainly printed material, record Davidovich's career accomplishments in fine arts and design.
  The scrapbook of career activities includes photographs of Davidovich and Herbert Read in Montreal, exhibition announcements, and correspondence. The design scrapbooks include book covers and a few mock-ups designed by Davidovich for publishers including Random House, for which he also designed a logo, and other photographs and samples of Davidovich's print design work.
  Scrapbook pages were removed from plastic enclosures for preservation reasons, but retain their original order.
  Scrapbooks have been digitized in entirety.
  - Career Activities, "Fine Arts Portfolio", circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 4, Folder 1)
  - Design, Publishing, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 4, Folder 2)
  - Design, Various Projects, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Design, Various Projects, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 4, Folder 3)
- Printed Materials, circa 1960-2008; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 2, OVs 3, 5
  Printed material documents Davidovich's career through books about him and his work, announcements and catalogs, press clippings, and other publicity, for exhibitions and other events he participated in throughout his career.
  The bulk of this series has been digitized. Items not digitized include the full text of publications for which only covers and/or relevant pages may be digitized.
  Printed materials are arranged by type and chronologically thereafter.
  - Art Reproductions, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Book, Jaime Davidovich by John Matturi, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Book, "Jaime Davidovich: Videotapes Catalogue", circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Book, The Live! Show, American Association of the Moving Image, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Brochures and Booklets, circa 1960-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Clippings, circa 1970-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Includes articles about Davidovich, SoHo, garbage art, and art events.
  - Clippings, "Art Places to Go", 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Clippings, Garbage Art, 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Clippings, "SoHo So What", 1977-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 3, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Davidovich, circa 1950s-circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Davidovich, 1972; 1984; 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Flyer, for 3 Mercer Street, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Periodicals, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Periodicals, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 3, Folder 5)
  - Posters, circa 1988-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5, Folder 4)
  - Press Releases, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Other Artists, Exhibition Announcements, circa 1990; 2007-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Other Artists, Poster, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5, Folder 5)